Welcome back.
잘 돌아왔어요
It's time to make our full agent framework.
에이전트 프레임워크를 만들 때가 됐어요
I'm super excited about this.
정말 기대돼요
It's pulling everything together that we've been doing before, and I think you'll be very happy with
지금까지 해 왔던 것처럼 모든 걸 잘 활용하고 있어요 결과에 아주 만족하실
the outcome.
거예요
Uh, so just a quick recap.
간단히 정리해 보죠
An agent framework.
프레임워크 요원요
The term agent I as I said, it's an umbrella term.
에이전트 I는 포괄적인 용어예요
It can refer to a bunch of different techniques.
다양한 기술을 참고할 수 있어요
Um, for example, it can be any of these five.
예를 들어 이 다섯 가지 중 아무거나요
It can be about breaking a complex problem into smaller steps with multiple models carrying out different
복잡한 문제를 여러 모델이 각기 다른 전문화된 작업을 수행하며 작은 단계로
specialized tasks.
단계화하는 거죠
It can be the ability for an LLM to have tools to give them extra capabilities.
LLM이 추가적인 기능을 부여할 도구를 갖는 기능일 수 있죠
It can be, uh, talking about the agent environment, which is the setup or the agent framework that
에이전트 환경에 대해 얘기할 수도 있습니다 에이전트가 협업을 할 수 있는 에이전트
allows agents to collaborate.
프레임워크죠
Um, it can be the idea that one LLM can act as a planner, dividing tasks into smaller ones, that
하나의 LLM이 플래너 역할을 하는 겁니다 작은 작업들로 나누고 전문가들이 직접
specialists that can themselves be llms or bits of software can carry out.
llm이 되거나 소프트웨어 조각을 수행하는 거죠
Um, and then there is another point here, which is that people talk about agentic AI when you're thinking
또 다른 요점은 에이전트 인공지능을 생각할
about an agent having its own autonomy agency, uh, beyond necessarily just responding to a prompt,
때 독자적인 기관을 떠올리는데 즉각적인 응답을 넘어서 메모리를
such as having memory, being able to sort of, uh, I don't know, do something like, uh, scrape
갖고 뉴스 정보를 검색해 웹을 긁고 주식을 매매할지
the web for news information and using that to make decisions about buying or selling stocks, something
결정하는 데 사용한다고 보면 돼요
like that.
그건 말하자면 요청 응답 채팅의 컨텍스트 밖에 존재하는 무언가예요
So these are all the kinds of ways that that these are the kinds of things people are referring to when
이런 식으로∙∙∙ 에이전트 AI와 에이전트의 사용에 대해 얘기할
they talk about agentic AI and the use of agents.
때 사람들이 언급하는 것들이죠
And what we're really doing here is we're talking about, uh, definitely number one and two there and
우리가 여기서 얘기하고 있는 건 1번과 2번이고 3번과
to a certain extent, numbers three and five.
5번도 어느 정도 있어요
But we're not we're not building an LLM that does the planning.
하지만 계획을 실행하는 LLM을 만드는 게 아니잖아요
That's not something we'll be doing in this session.
이번 시간엔 그런 걸 안 할 거예요
So, uh, this should be somewhat familiar to you because this is the chat method that's quite close
이건 익숙하실 거예요 채팅 메서드거든요 전에 있던 것과 꽤 비슷하죠
So you'll recognize a few things about this.
몇 가지 눈에 띄는 게 있어요
This section here is the usual chat radio function that we know really well.
이 섹션은 우리가 잘 아는 라디오 채팅 함수예요
It takes a message and a history, and it, uh, sort of unpacks that history into the format that OpenAI
메시지와 히스토리를 취하고 그 히스토리를 오픈AI가 기대하는 포맷으로
will expect and then calls the response.
풀어낸 다음 응답을 호출해요
This part here will also look familiar to you because it's our use of tools.
이 부분도 익숙하실 겁니다 도구를 사용하는 곳이니까요
It's where we find out if the model wants to call a tool, and if so, we handle that tool.
모델이 도구를 호출하길 원하는지 알고 있다면 그 도구를 다루죠
Uh, but there's one little extra line just inserted in there, and it's that line there that what we're
여기 한 줄 더 있는데요 여기서 말씀 드리고 싶은
going to say is if the person does, if the model decides it needs to, to run the tool to find the
건 만약 고객이 티켓 가격을 찾기 위해 툴을 실행해야
price of a ticket, then we will also have the, um, artist generate an image to represent that city
한다면 아티스트가 그 도시를 나타내는 이미지를 생성하도록 할 거예요
So there we have it.
자, 됐어요
Uh, that's, uh that's nice.
그거 좋네요
And also, now, if you remember before I told you there was a reason I passed back city that you're
그리고 제가 전에 얘기했던 걸 기억하신다면 제가 돌아온 이유를 곧 알게
going to find out.
되실 거예요
Here it is.
여기 있네요
That's why I needed the city to pass it to the artist.
그래서 시가 예술가에게 넘겨야 했어요
Um, and then, uh, this is all exactly the same.
그리고 이건 전부 똑같아요
There's one more tiny change.
한 가지 더 있어요
Which is this here, which is that, uh, once I've collected the response from the model, I then call
여기 있는 이 모델에서 반응을 수집한 다음 토크 커뮤니티에
talker to make sure that we speak the response.
전화해 반응을 확인하죠
So that is our chat.
이게 우리 대화예요
Uh, let's run that.
그걸 실행해 보죠
Now, this, I should say, since I've always showed off about how easy Gradio is, this code is a little
비트가 얼마나 쉬운지 늘 자랑했듯이 이 코드는 좀 더 복잡해요
You may notice the reason is because we're now because we want to do a little bit more and show images.
그 이유는 비트를 더 많이 사용하고 이미지를 보여주기 위해서예요
We're going outside the default, the sort of off the shelf, uh, chat user interface that Gradio provides
기본 설정 밖으로 나가보죠 규격화된 채팅 사용자 인터페이스 같은 건데 그라디오가 제공해요
for us.
인터페이스는 우리가 직접 만들어야 해요
And as a result, I've had to put together this interface that kind of puts together the various components
그 결과 이 인터페이스를 구성해야 했어요 input이나 버튼 같은 다양한 구성
like the input and the buttons.
요소를 구성하는 거죠
But what I'll say is this is still actually super straightforward.
하지만 이건 여전히 아주 간단해요
It still reads like English.
영어처럼 들려요
It's very clear what's going on.
무슨 일인지 뻔하죠
You'll see everything that's happening here, and hopefully this will be quite readable for you.
여기서 일어나는 모든 일을 볼 수 있어요 읽을 수 있길 바라요
And you can use this to build more sophisticated chats, more sophisticated UIs yourself.
이걸 이용해 더 복잡한 채팅이나 더 복잡한 UI를 만들 수 있어요
So with that background, we now are going to run this to it's running and we'll bring that up.
이 배경으로 이걸 실행∙∙∙ 실행되고 있어요 불러오죠
And here we have our chat with our new assistant.
새 비서와 대화하는 모습이네요
Let's give it a try.
한번 해 보죠
Hello.
안녕하세요
How can I assist you today.
무엇을 도와드릴까요?
You like that?
맘에 들어요?
It spoke to us.
우리에게 말을 걸었어요
There we go.
됐어요
That's the first use of an agent.
에이전트 사용은 처음이죠
We had a specialist model that's able to create, uh, audio, and we integrated that with our chatbot
오디오를 만드는 전문 모델이 있었는데 그걸 챗봇과 통합해서 우리에게
so that it was able to speak back to us.
말을 걸 수 있게 했어요
Great choice.
탁월한 선택이에요
Would you like to know the to the ticket price for a return trip to London?
런던 왕복 비행기 표 가격을 알고 싶으세요?
There we go.
됐어요
That's entertaining, let's say.
재미있다고 해두죠
We know there's a pause.
잠시 멈추죠
Here we go.
시작할게요
A return ticket to London is priced at 799.
런던 왕복 항공권은 799달러예요
And there we have it.
다 됐어요
A return ticket to London is priced at $7.99.
런던 왕복 항공권은 7달러예요 99살요
And there is the image.
이미지가 나오네요
And that image looks spectacular.
정말 장관이에요
A London bus in the middle.
런던 버스예요
It's got Big Ben.
빅벤도 있어요
It's got the bridge.
다리도 있어요
It's got, uh.
네
Yeah, I can see taxi there.
저기 택시가 보여요
It's just a great montage of images.
여러 이미지의 멋진 몽타주예요
Uh, and so I find this to be very compelling indeed, a wonderful example of what we're able to achieve
그래서 저는 이 비트가 아주 흥미롭다고 생각합니다 소량의 코드만으로 무엇을 이룰 수 있는지 보여주는
with just a little bit of code.
훌륭한 예죠
And so I present to you a multimodal app, complete with audio and some images running as part of what
다중 모듈 앱을 소개합니다 비행기의 인공지능 보조와 통신할
is a in a, in a small way, a multimodal agentic framework for talking to an airline AI assistant.
때 음성과 이미지가 포함된 다중 모듈 에이전트 프레임워크죠
Great work.
수고했어요
I'll see you for the challenge of the week and the wrap up.
이번 주의 도전과 마무리에서 다시 만나요